Guide to the Charles Reynolds Brown Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Charles Reynolds Brown Papers
1860-1957
RG 37
Yale University Divinity School Library
9
(17 boxes)
The collection documents Brown's long and active career as a Congregational minister, Dean of Yale Divinity School and author. Prominent correspondents include William Lyon Phelps, Washington Gladden, Booker T. Washington, Henry Sloane Coffin, Herbert Hoover, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John R. Mott, William H. Taft, Theodore Roosevelt and Luther A. Weigle. Charles Reynolds Brown was born in Bethany, West Virginia on October 1, 1862. He was educated at the University of Iowa and Boston University, and received several honorary degrees. He was a prominent Protestant clergyman in Congregational churches across the United States, Dean of Yale Divinity School (1911-1928) and an author. He served as Moderator of the National Council of Congregational Churches and as Chairman of the Congregational Education Society. He died on November 28, 1950.
Brown, Charles Reynolds, 1862-1950
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Brown family.
Biographical / Historical
1862 Oct 1 Born in Bethany, W. Va., son of Benjamin F. and Sarah T. Brown
1883 A.BUniversity of Iowa
1886 A.M., University of Iowa
1889 S.T.B., Boston University
1889-1892 Pastor of Wesley Chapel, Cincinnati, Ohio
1892-1896 Pastor of Winthrop Congregational Church, Boston
1896 Sep 23 Married Alice Tufts
1896-1910 Pastor of First Congregational Church, Oakland, Ca.
1897 Professional study in Egypt and Palestine
1911-1928 Dean of the Yale Divinity School -Pastor of Yale University Church for twelve years
1913-1915 Moderator of the National Council of Congregational Churches
xx Honorary degrees from Yale, Boston U., Brown, Mills College, Oberlin, U. of Vermont, Wesleyan
xx Chairman of Congregational Education Society
1928-1950 During the years of his retirement Brown continued to preach and write extensively. He was considered to be one of the nation's foremost Protestant clergymen. Dean Emeritus
1950 Nov 28 Died
Scope and Contents
The first series, Correspondence, is divided into Family Correspondence and General Correspondence. Within each of these sections the correspondence of Brown's wife is separated from his own. The Family Correspondence dates from 1886 to 1944. It includes letters to or from Brown, his wife, mother, father, sister, niece and cousins. Brown wrote long and detailed letters to family members regarding his trips abroad in l894 and l897 and regarding the San Francisco earthquake in 1906. During trips to Europe in 1911 and 1931 Brown wrote daily to his wife.
General Correspondence dates from l894 to 1951 and consists primarily of letters received by Brown. The letters in this section are useful for tracing the development of Brown's own career. Factors influencing his decisions first to accept a call to Oakland and later to become dean of the Divinity School are evident in his correspondence with friends and colleagues. Matters regarding Brown's extensive publications and his involvement in the affairs of the Congregational Church are also dealt with in the General Correspondence section. An abbreviated list of notable correspondents would include: Henry Sloane Coffin (1919, 1922, 1943), Alfred Coit (1920), David E. Fitzgerald (1922\Washington Gladden (1906), Herbert Hoover (1917, 1920, 1940), John R. Mott (1921), William Lyon Phelps (1928, 1939), John D. Rockefeller Jr. (1919), Theodore Roosevelt (1926, 1932, 1933), William H. Taft (1914, 1916, 1923, 1926) and Booker T. Washington (1902).
The second series, Notebooks and Journals, dates from 1883 to 1947 and includes material written by Brown and by his wife. Engagement record books and a record of sermons preached document Brown's long and active life. Other notebooks include notes for sermon illustrations. The journals of Alice Tufts Brown record daily activities during trips abroad in l897, l898, 1928, and 1931.
The Writings of Series III are divided into four sections.
a) Addresses and Sermons (1891-1946, n.d.); primarily in manuscript form.
b) Published works (l898-1944, n.d.); primarily in printed form with a few typescript drafts
c) Miscellaneous (1860-1946, n.d.); including notes for lectures and published works, an unpublished manuscript, publication agreements and a few writings by others.
d) Reviews of Brown's books (1924-1944, n.d.)
The material in this series supplemented by the newspaper clippings in bound volumes 1 through 7 gives a reasonably complete picture of Brown's career as a preacher and writer. The collection contains little which deals with issues or events at Yale Divinity School during Brown's tenure as dean.
The fourth series, Personal Items and Memorabilia (1883-1951, n.d.), includes biographical material, memorabilia, newspaper clippings which spotlight important events in Brown's career, and one folder of photographs.
Bound volumes 1 through 7 contain primarily newspaper clippings about Brown, by him or reviewing his publications. These volumes are recorded on microfilm. Bound volume 8 is apparently a record of members received by the churches Brown served from 1889 to 1896. Bound volumes 9 and 10 contain the International Sunday School Lessons written by Brown from 1911 to 1917. Bound volumes 8 - 10 and microfilm (vol. 1-7) are found in the oversize box.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1886-1951
II. Notebooks and Journals, 1883-1947
III. Writings, 1860-1946, n.d.
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1883-1951, n.d.
Congregational churches -- United States; Authors; Clergy; Deans; Brown, Charles Reynolds, 1862-1950; Coffin, Henry Sloane, 1877-1954; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Congregational Education Society; Yale University. Divinity School; National Council of Congregational Churches ( 1865 Boston, Mass.)
- Correspondence, 1886-1951; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Family Correspondence is arranged chronologically with the recipient or sender other than Brown noted on the folder. The correspondence of Alice Tufts Brown follows that of her husband.General Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Notable correspondents are indicated on the folder headings. The correspondence of Alice Tufts Brown again follows that of her husband.
  - Correspondence: Family
    - CRB: To/from mother, 1886-1890 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - CRB: To parents ret trip abroad, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - CRB: To fiancee, father, sister incl. ret trip abroad, 1896-1897 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - CRB: To parents ret trip to Hawaii, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - CRB: To mother incl. ret San Francisco earthquake, 1906-1907 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - CRB: To parents, sister ret trip abroad, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - CRB: To/from mother, sister, 1910-1911 Jun (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - CRB: To wife from Europe, 1911 Jul (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - CRB: To wife from Europe, 1911 Aug (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - CRB: To wife from Europe, 1931 Jul. Aug (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - CRB: From cousins, 1939-1944 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - CRB: To mother, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - ATB: Incl. to parents, 1906-1908 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - ATB: To sister-in-law, niece, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: General
    - CRB: Re. call to Oakland church, 1894-1896 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - CRB: Re. publications l898-, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - CRB: Incl. from Booker T. Washington, Frank K. Sanders, 1901-1905 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - CRB: Incl. from Washington Gladden, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - CRB: Incl. from Geo. Gordon, 1907-1908 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - CRB: Re. publications, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - CRB: Incl. ret leaving Calif., 1910 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - CRB: Incl. from Charles Eliot, 1911-1912 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - CRB: Incl. from Wm. H. Taft, 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - CRB: Incl. from Arthur Twining Hadley Dotha Bushnell Hillyer, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - CRB: Incl. from Herbert Hoover, Charles E. Jefferson, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - CRB: Incl. from John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur T. Hadley, Henry Sloane Coffin, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - CRB: Incl. from Herbert Hoover, Alfred Colt, John R. Mott, 1920-1921 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - CRB: Incl. from David E. Fitzgerald, Henry S. Coffin, Wm. H. Taft, 1922-1923 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - CRB: Incl. from Theodore Roosevelt, Wm. H. Taft, 1924-1926 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - CRB: Incl. ret publications, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - CRB: Incl. from James R. Angell, Wm. Lyon Phelps, Luther A. Weigle, 1928-1929 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - CRB: Incl. from Charles McLean Warren, 1930-1931 May (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - CRB: Incl. from James R. Angell, Theodore Roosevelt, 1931 Jun-1932 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - CRB: Incl. from Theodore Roosevelt, 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - CRB, 1935-1937 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - CRB: Incl. from Wm. H. Danforth, Wm. Lyon Phelps, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - CRB: Incl. from Herbert Hoover, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - CRB: Incl. from Harry Emerson Fosdick, 1941-1942 Jun (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - CRB: Re. his 80th birthday, 1942 Sep-Dec (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - CRB: Incl. from Henry S. Coffin, Anson Phelps Stokes, 1943-1949 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence: General
    - CRB: Incl. from Henry S. Coffin, Harry Emerson Fosdick, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - ATB, 1941-1957, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Notebooks and Journals, 1883-1947; Series II
  Notebooks belonging to Brown are arranged chronologically within each of three sections:a) Engagement record books; b) Record book of sermons preached; c) Miscellaneous notebooks. The fourth section in this series, the travel journals of Alice Tufts Brown, is also arranged chronologically.
  - Engagement Record Books
    - CRB: Engagement Records LA CRB: Engagement Records 1894-1913, 1883-1893 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - CRB: Engagement Records, 1914-1919 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - CRB: Engagement Records, 1920-1926 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - CRB: Engagement Records, 1927-1932 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - CRB: Engagement Records, 1933-1938 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - CRB: Engagement Records, 1939-1947 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Record Book of Sermons Preached
    - CRB: Record of sermons preached, 1912-1945 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Miscellaneous Notebooks
    - CRB: Miscellaneous notebooks, 1908, 1910, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - CRB: Miscellaneous notebooks, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Travel Journals of Alice Tufts Brown
    - ATB: Journals from trips abroad, 1897 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - ATB: Journals from trips abroad, 1897, 1898 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - ATB: Journals from trips abroad, 1928-1931 (Box 6, Folder 55)
- Writings, 1860-1946, n.d.; Series III
  a) Addresses and Sermons are arranged alphabetically by title with dates indicated when available; b) Published works are arranged chronologically; c) Miscellaneous writings are arranged alphabetically by type of material, i.e. notes, publication agreements,unpublished manuscript, etc.d) Reviews of Brown's books are arranged alphabetically by the title of the book being reviewed. One folder of miscellaneous reviews follows those arranged by title.
  - Addresses and Sermons
    - A (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - B-Ch, 1918-1934, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Co-Da, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - De-Dr, 1943, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - E, 1898-1946, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Fa, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Fi-Gi, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Go-Ha, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - He-Je, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - Jo-Ju, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - K-Le, 1898, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - Li-Ma, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - Me-N, 1924, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - O-Pa, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - Pe-Pu, 1923, 1933, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - R, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 71)
    - S-So, 1917, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 72)
    - Sp-Su, 1932, no.. (Box 9, Folder 73)
    - T, 1891-1943, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 74)
    - U-We, 1945, 1946, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - Wha-Whe, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 76)
    - Who-Y, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 77)
    - Untitled (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - Published Works
    - Various, 1898-1944, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 79-85)
    - Various, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 86)
  - Miscellaneous Writings
    - Notes for The Art of Preaching, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 87)
    - Notes on"Care of the Parish", n.d. (Box 11, Folder 88)
    - Notes; incl. on Methodist polity, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 89)
    - Publication agreements and records; incl. list of published works, 1898-1946, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 90)
    - Unpublished manuscript, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 91)
    - Writings by others, 1860-1942, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 92)
  - Reviews of CRB's Books
    - Being Made Over, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 93)
    - Dreams Come True, 1944 (Box 12, Folder 94)
    - Finding Ourselves, 1935 (Box 12, Folder 95)
    - Have We Outgrown Religion?, 1933-1936 (Box 12, Folder 96)
    - Ten Short Stories From the Bible, 1925 (Box 12, Folder 97)
    - Miscellaneous, 1924-1939, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 98)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1883-1951, n.d.; Series IV
  a) Biographical material is arranged chronologically; b) Memorabilia is arranged by type of item; c) Newspaper clippings are divided into biographical, regarding sermons and addresses, and miscellaneous. The clippings are arranged chronologically within these sections.; d) Photographs are arranged chronologically.
  - Biographical Material
    - Various, 1892-1951,n.d. (Box 13, Folder 99-101)
  - Memorabilia
    - Marked Bibles belonging to CRB and ATB, 1900, 1929, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 102)
    - Incl. Masonic Material, 1883-1937 (Box 13, Folder 103)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Biographical, 1892-1939, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 104)
    - Biographical, 1950, 1951 (Box 14, Folder 105)
    - Regarding sermons and addresses, 1896-1943, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 106)
    - Regarding sermons and addresses (Box 14, Folder 107)
    - Regarding lecture about Lincoln, 1936-1950, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 108)
    - Miscellaneous, 1906, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 109)
  - Photographs and additional memorabilia
    - Photographs, 1921, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 110)
    - Honorary degrees and citations; Guest books; Bon voyage greetings written by friends of the Browns on occasion of their trip to Japan; Photo of League of Nations traveling group (boxes 15 and 16), 1910-1939 (Box 15)
    - Honorary degrees and citations; Guest books; Bon voyage greetings written by friends of the Browns on occasion of their trip to Japan; Photo of League of Nations traveling group (boxes 15 and 16) (Box 16)
    - Bound Volumes 8-10, Microfilm (vols. 1-7) (Box 17)